<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
 <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
 <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
 <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?> 
 <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
 <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>  
 <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="no" ?>


<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-dots-use-cases-01.txt">

<front>
<title abbrev="DOTS Use cases">Use cases for DDoS Open Threat Signaling</title>

     <author fullname="Roland Dobbins" initials="R." surname="Dobbins" role="editor">
     <organization>Arbor Networks</organization>
     <address>
     <postal>
     <street>30 Raffles Place</street>
	 <street>Level 17 Chevron House</street>
     <city>Singapore 048622</city>
     <country>Singapore</country>
     </postal>
     <email>rdobbins@arbor.net</email>
     </address>
     </author>
 
    <author fullname="Stefan Fouant" initials="S." surname="Fouant">
      <organization> Corero Network Security </organization>
      <address>
        <email> Stefan.Fouant@corero.com </email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Daniel Migault" initials="D." surname="Migault">
      <organization> Ericsson </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street> 8400 boulevard Decarie</street>
          <city> Montreal</city>
           <region>QC</region>
         <code> H4P 2N2 </code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone> +1 514-452-2160 </phone>
        <email> daniel.migault@ericsson.com </email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Robert Moskowitz" initials="R." surname="Moskowitz">
      <organization>HTT Consulting
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
        <street></street>
        <city>Oak Park</city>
        <region>MI</region>
		<code>48237</code>
        <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>rgm@labs.htt-consult.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

	<author fullname="Nik Teague" initials="N." surname="Teague">
	  <organization>Verisign Inc</organization>
	  <address>
	  <postal>
	  <street>12061 Bluemont Way</street>
	  <city>Reston</city>
      <region>VA</region>
      <code>20190</code>
	  <country>USA</country>
	  </postal>
	  <phone>+44 791 763 5384</phone>
	  <email>nteague@verisign.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

     <author fullname="Liang Xia" initials="L." surname="Xia">
        <organization>Huawei</organization>
        <address>
        <postal>
        <street>No. 101, Software Avenue, Yuhuatai District</street>
        <city>Nanjing</city>
        <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>Frank.xialiang@huawei.com</email>
        </address>
        </author>

<date year="2016" />
   <area>Security Area</area>
    <workgroup> DOTS WG</workgroup>
    <keyword>RFC</keyword>
     <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
     <keyword>I-D</keyword>
     <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
<t>
	This document delineates principal and ancillary use cases for DDoS 
	Open Threat Signaling (DOTS), a communications protocol intended to 
	facilitate the programmatic, coordinated mitigation of Distributed 
	Denial of Service (DDoS) attacks via a standards-based mechanism. 
	DOTS is purposely designed to support requests for DDoS mitigation 
	services and status updates across inter-organizational 
	administrative boundaries.
</t>
    </abstract>

</front>
  <middle>

<section title="Introduction" anchor="intro"> 
<t>
   Currently, distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attack mitigation 
   solutions/services are largely based upon siloed, proprietary 
   communications paradigms which result in vendor/service lock-in, and 
   as a side-effect make the configuration, provisioning, operation, 
   and activation of these solutions a highly manual and often time- 
   consuming process.  Additionally, coordination of multiple DDoS 
   mitigation solutions/services simultaneously engaged in defending 
   the same organization against DDoS attacks is fraught with both 
   technical and process-related hurdles which greatly increase 
   operational complexity and often result in suboptimal DDoS attack 
   mitigation efficacy.
</t>
<t>
   The DDoS Open Threat Signaling (DOTS) effort is intended to 
   facilitate interoperability between DDoS solutions/services by 
   providing a standards-based, programmatic communications mechanism 
   for the invitation and termination of heterogeneous DDoS attack 
   mitigation systems and services.  This allows for a much higher 
   degree of automation and concomitant efficacy and rapidity of DDoS 
   attack mitigation involving multiple DDoS mitigation systems and 
   services than is currently the norm, as well as providing additional 
   benefits such as automatic DDoS mitigation service registration and 
   provisioning.  It should be noted that DOTS is not in and of itself 
   intended to perform orchestration functions duplicative of the 
   functionality being developed by the [I2NSF] WG; rather, DOTS is 
   intended to allow devices, services, and applications to request 
   mitigation assistance and receive mitigation status updates from 
   systems of this nature.
</t>
<t>
   This document provides an overview of common DDoS mitigation system/ 
   service deployment and operational models which are in use today, 
   but which are currently limited in scope to a single vendor or 
   service provider and are often highly manual in nature, which can 
   lead to miscommunications, misconfigurations, and delays in bringing 
   mitigation services to bear against an attack.  The introduction of 
   DOTS into these scenarios will reduce reaction times and the risks 
   associated with manual processes, simplify the use of multiple types 
   of DDoS mitigation systems and services as required, and make 
   practical the simultaneous use multiple DDoS mitigation systems and 
   services as circumstances warrant.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="terms" title="Terminology and Acronyms">
	<section title="Requirements Terminology">
	<t>
		The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL 
		NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and 
		"OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described 
		in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
	</t> 
	</section> 
	<section title="Acronyms">
	<t>
		This document makes use of the same terminology and definitions 
		as <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements" />, except where 
		noted.
	</t>
	</section> 
</section>

<section title="Use Cases">
<t>
	This section provides a high-level overview of likely use cases and 
	deployment scenarios for DOTS-enabled DDoS mitigation services.  It 
	should be noted that DOTS servers may be standalone entities which, 
	upon receiving a DOTS mitigation service request from a DOTS 
	client, proceed to initiate DDoS mitigation service by 
	communicating directly or indirectly with DDoS mitigators, and 
	likewise terminate the service upon receipt of a DOTS service 
	termination request; conversely, the DDoS mitigators themselves may 
	incorporate DOTS servers and/or DOTS clients.  The mechanisms by 
	which DOTS servers initiate and terminate DDoS mitigation service 
	with DDoS mitigators is beyond the scope of this document.
</t>
<t>
	All of the primary use cases described in this section are derived 
	from current, real-world DDoS mitigation functionality, 
	capabilities, and operational models.
</t>
<t>
	The posited ancillary use cases described in this section are 
	reasonable and highly desirable extrapolations of the functionality 
	of baseline DOTS capabilities, and are readily attainable in the 
	near term.
</t>
<t>
	Each of the primary and ancillary use cases described in this 
	section may be read as involving one or more DDoS mitigation 
	service providers; DOTS makes multi-provider coordinated DDoS 
	defenses much more effective and practical due to abstraction of 
	the particulars of a given DDoS mitigation service/solution set.
</t>
<t>
	Both the primary and ancillary use cases may be facilitated by 
	direct DOTS client - DOTS server communications or via DOTS relays 
	deployed in order to aggregate DOTS mitigation service 
	requests/responses, to mediate between stateless and stateful 
	underlying transport protocols, to aggregate multiple DOTS requests 
	and/or responses, to filter DOTS requests and/or responses via 
	configured policy mechanisms, or some combination of these 
	functions.
</t>
<t>
	All DOTS messages exchanged between the DOTS clients and DOTS 
	servers in these use cases may be communicated directly between 
	DOTS clients and servers, or mediated by one or more DOTS relays 
	residing on the network of the originating network, the network 
	where upstream DDoS mitigation service takes place, an intervening 
	network or networks, or some combination of the above.
</t>
<t>
	DOTS is intended to apply to both inter- and intra-domain DDoS 
	attack mitigation scenarios.  The technical and operational 
	requirements for inter- and intra-domain DOTS communications are 
	identical.  The main difference is administrative in nature; 
	although it should be noted that provisioning challenges which are 
	typically associated with inter- domain DOTS communications 
	relationships may also apply in intra- domain deployment scenarios, 
	based upon organizational factors.  All of the same complexities 
	surrounding authentication and authorization can apply in both 
	contexts, including considerations such as network access policies 
	to allow DOTS communications, DOTS transport selection (including 
	considerations of the implications of link congestion if a stateful 
	DOTS transport option is selected), etc.  Registration of 
	well-known ports for DOTS transports per <xref target="RFC6335"/> 
	should be considered in light of these challenges.
</t>
<t>
	It should also be noted that DOTS does not directly ameliorate the 
	various administrative challenges required for successful DDoS 
	attack mitigation. Letters of authorization, RADB updates, DNS zone 
	delegations, alteration of network access policies, technical 
	configurations required to facilitate network traffic diversion and 
	re-injection, etc., are all outside the scope of DOTS. DOTS may, 
	however, prove useful in automating the registration of DOTS 
	clients with DOTS servers, as well as in the automatic provisioning 
	of situationally- appropriate DDoS defenses and countermeasures. 
	This ancillary DOTS functionality is described in <xref 
	target="Ancillary" />.
</t>
<t>
	Many of the 'external' administrative challenges associated with 
	establishing workable DDoS attack mitigation service may be 
	addressed by work currently in progress in the I2RS and I2NSF WGs.  
	Interested parties may wish to consider tracking those efforts, and 
	coordination with both I2RS and I2NSF is highly desirable.
</t>
<t>
	Note that all the use-cases in this document are universal in 
	nature. They apply equally to endpoint networks, transit backbone 
	providers, cloud providers, broadband access providers, ASPs, CDNs, 
	etc.  They are not specific to particular business models, 
	topological models, or application types, and are deliberately 
	generalizable.  Both networks targeted for attack as well as any 
	adjacent or topologically distant networks involved in a given 
	scenario may be either single- or multi-homed.   In the 
	accompanying vector illustrations incorporated into 
	draft-ietf-dots-use-cases-01.pdf, specific business and topological 
	models are described in order to provide context.
</t>
<t>
	Likewise, both DOTS itself and the use cases described in this 
	document are completely independent of technologies utilized for 
	the detection, classification, traceback, and mitigation of DDoS 
	attacks.  Flow telemetry such as NetFlow and IPFIX, direct 
	full-packet analysis, log-file analysis, indirection manual 
	observation, etc. can and will be enablers for detection, 
	classification and traceback. Intelligent DDoS mitigation systems 
	(IDMSes), flowspec, S/RTBH, ACLs, and other network traffic 
	manipulation tools and techniques may be used for DDoS attack 
	mitigation.  BGP, flowspec, DNS, inline deployment, and various 
	'NFV' technologies may be used for network traffic diversion into 
	mitigation centers or devices in applicable scenarios; GRE, MPLS, 
	'NFV', inline deployment and other techniques may be utilized for 
	'cleaned' traffic re-injection to its intended destination.
</t>
<t>
	The scope, format, and content of all DOTS message types cited in 
	this document must be codified by the DOTS WG.
</t>
<t>
	The following use cases are intended to inform the DOTS 
	requirements described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements" 
	/>.
</t>

    <section title="Primary Use Cases">

	<section title="Automatic or Operator-Assisted CPE or PE Mitigators 
	Request Upstream DDoS Mitigation Services">
<t>
	One or more CPE or PE mitigators with DOTS client capabilities may 
	be configured to signal to one or more DOTS servers in order to 
	request upstream DDoS mitigation service initiation during an 
	attack when DDoS attack volumes and/or attack characteristics 
	exceed the capabilities of such CPE mitigators.  DDoS mitigation 
	service may be terminated either automatically or manually via a 
	DOTS mitigation service termination request initiated by the 
	mitigator when it has been determined that the DDoS attack has 
	ended.
	<list style="format (%c)">
	<t>
		A DDoS attack is initiated against online properties of an 
		organization which has deployed DOTS-client-capable DDoS 
		mitigators.
	</t>
	<t>
		CPE or PE DDoS mitigators detect, classify, and begin 
		mitigating the DDoS attack.
	</t>
	<t>
		CPE or PE DDoS mitigators determine that their capacity and/or 
		capability to mitigate the DDoS attack is insufficient, and 
		utilize their DOTS client functionality to send a DOTS 
		mitigation service initiation request to one or more DOTS 
		servers residing on one or more upstream transit networks, peer 
		networks, or overlay MSSP networks. This DOTS mitigation 
		service initiation request may be automatically initiated by 
		the CPE or PE DDoS mitigators, or may be manually triggered by 
		personnel of the requesting organization in response to an 
		alert from the mitigators (the mechanism by which this process 
		takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers which receive the DOTS mitigation service 
		initiation requests determine that they have been configured to 
		honor requests from the requesting CPE or PE mitigators, and 
		initiate situationally-appropriate DDoS mitigation service on 
		their respective networks (the mechanism by which this process 
		takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS service status message to the 
		requesting CPE or PE mitigators indicating that upstream DDoS 
		mitigation service has been initiated.
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the DOTS servers 
		regularly transmit DOTS mitigation status updates to the 
		requesting CPE or PE mitigators.
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the CPE or PE 
		mitigators may optionally regularly transmit DOTS mitigation 
		efficacy updates to the relevant DOTS servers.
	</t>
	<t>
		When the upstream DDoS mitigators determine that the DDoS 
		attack has ceased, they indicate this change in status to their 
		respective DOTS servers (the mechanism by which this process 
		takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to 
		the CPE or PE mitigators indicating that the DDoS attack has 
		ceased.
	</t>
	<t>
		The CPE or PE DDoS mitigators transmit a DOTS mitigation 
		service termination request to the DOTS servers. This DOTS 
		mitigation service termination request may be automatically 
		initiated by the CPE or PE DDoS mitigators, or may be manually 
		triggered by personnel of the requesting organization in 
		response to an alert from the mitigators or a management system 
		which monitors them (the mechanism by which this process takes 
		place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers terminate DDoS mitigation service on their 
		respective networks (the mechanism by which this process takes 
		place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to 
		the CPE or PE mitigators indicating that DDoS mitigation 
		services have been terminated.
	</t>
	<t>
		The CPE or PE DDoS mitigators transmit a DOTS mitigation 
		termination status acknowledgement to the DOTS servers.
	</t>
	</list>
</t>
</section>

	<section title="Automatic or Operator-Assisted CPE or PE Network 
	Infrastructure Element Request to Upstream Mitigator">

<t>
	CPE or PE network infrastructure elements such as routers, 
	switches, load-balancers, firewalls, 'IPSes', etc. which have the 
	capability to detect and classify DDoS attacks and which have DOTS 
	client capabilities may be configured to signal to one or more DOTS 
	servers in order to request upstream DDoS mitigation service 
	initiation during an attack.  DDoS mitigation service may be 
	terminated either automatically or manually via a DOTS mitigation 
	service termination request initiated by the network element when 
	it has been determined that the DDoS attack has ended.
</t>
<t>
	In this use-case, the network elements involved are not engaged in 
	mitigating DDoS attack traffic.  They are signaling for upstream 
	attack mitigation assistance.  This can be an inter- or intra- 
	domain use-case.
	<list style="format (%c)">
	<t>
		A DDoS attack is initiated against online properties of an 
		organization with DOTS-client-capable network infrastructure 
		elements deployed.
	</t>
	<t>
		The network infrastructure elements utilize their DOTS client 
		functionality to send a DOTS mitigation service initiation 
		request to one or more DOTS servers residing on one or more 
		upstream transit networks, peer networks, or overlay MSSP 
		networks, either directly or via intermediate DOTS relays 
		residing upon the requesting organization's network, the 
		upstream mitigation provider's network, or both.  The scope, 
		format, and content of these messages must be codified by the 
		DOTS WG.  This DOTS mitigation service initiation request may 
		be automatically initiated by the network infrastructure 
		elements, or may be manually triggered by personnel of the 
		requesting organization in response to an alert from the 
		network elements or a management system which monitors them 
		(the mechanism by which this process takes place is beyond the 
		scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers which receive the DOTS mitigation service 
		initiation requests determine that they have been configured to 
		honor requests from the requesting network infrastructure 
		elements, and initiate situationally-appropriate DDoS 
		mitigation service on their respective networks (the mechanism 
		by which this process takes place is beyond the scope of this 
		document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS service status message to the 
		requesting network infrastructure elements indicating that 
		upstream DDoS mitigation service has been initiated.
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the DOTS servers 
		regularly transmit DOTS mitigation status updates to the 
		requesting requesting network infrastructure elements.
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the network 
		infrastructure elements may optionally regularly transmit DOTS 
		mitigation efficacy updates to the relevant DOTS servers.
	</t>
	<t>
		When the upstream DDoS mitigators determine that the DDoS 
		attack has ceased, they indicate this change in status to their 
		respective DOTS servers (the mechanism by which this process 
		takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to 
		the network infrastructure elements indicating that the DDoS 
		attack has ceased.
	</t>
	<t>
		The network infrastructure elements transmit a DOTS mitigation 
		service termination request to the DOTS servers.  This DOTS 
		mitigation service termination request may be automatically 
		initiated by the network infrastructure elements, or may be 
		manually triggered by personnel of the requesting organization 
		in response to an alert from the mitigators (the mechanism by 
		which this process takes place is beyond the scope of this 
		document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers terminate DDoS mitigation service on their 
		respective networks (the mechanism by which this process takes 
		place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to 
		the network infrastructure elements indicating that DDoS 
		mitigation services have been terminated.
	</t>
	<t>
		The network infrastructure elements transmit a DOTS mitigation 
		termination status acknowledgement to the DOTS servers.
	</t>
	</list>
</t>

    </section>

	<section title="Automatic or Operator-Assisted CPE or PE Attack 
	Telemetry Detection/Classification System Request to Upstream 
	Mitigator">

<t>
	CPE or PE Attack Telemetry Detection/Classification Systems which 
	have DOTS client capabilities may be configured so that upon 
	detecting and classifying a DDoS attack, they signal one or more 
	DOTS servers in order to request upstream DDoS mitigation service 
	initiation.  DDoS mitigation service may be terminated either 
	automatically or manually via a DOTS mitigation service termination 
	request initiated by the Attack Telemetry Detection/Classification 
	System when it has been determined that the DDoS attack has ended.
</t>   
<t>
	In this use-case, the Attack Telemetry Detection/Classification 
	does not possess any inherent capability to mitigate DDoS attack 
	traffic, and is signaling for upstream mitigation assistance.  This 
	can be an inter- or intra-domain use-case.
	<list style="format (%c)">
	<t>
		A DDoS attack is initiated against online properties of an 
		organization with DOTS-client-capable CPE or PE Attack 
		Telemetry Detection/Classification Systems deployed.
	</t>
	<t>
		The CPE or PE Attack Telemetry Detection/Classification Systems 
		utilize their DOTS client functionality to send a DOTS 
		mitigation service initiation request to one or more DOTS 
		servers residing on one or more upstream transit networks, peer 
		networks, or overlay MSSP networks, either directly or via 
		intermediate DOTS relays residing upon the requesting 
		organization's network, the upstream mitigation provider's 
		network, or both.   This DOTS mitigation service initiation 
		request may be automatically initiated by the CPE or PE Attack 
		Telemetry Detection/Classification Systems, or may be manually 
		triggered by personnel of the requesting organization in 
		response to an alert from the CPE or PE Attack Telemetry 
		Detection/Classification Systems (the mechanism by which this 
		process takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers which receive the DOTS mitigation service 
		initiation requests determine that they have been configured to 
		honor requests from the requesting CPE or PE Attack Telemetry 
		Detection/Classification Systems, and initiate situationally- 
		appropriate DDoS mitigation service on their respective 
		networks (the mechanism by which this process takes place is 
		beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS service status message to the 
		requesting CPE or PE Attack Telemetry Detection/Classification 
		Systems indicating that upstream DDoS mitigation service has 
		been initiated.
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the DOTS servers 
		regularly transmit DOTS mitigation status updates to the 
		requesting CPE or PE Attack Telemetry Detection/Classification 
		Systems.
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the CPE or PE Attack 
		Telemetry Detection/Classification Systems may optionally 
		regularly transmit DOTS mitigation efficacy updates to the 
		relevant DOTS servers.
	</t>
	<t>
		When the upstream DDoS mitigators determine that the DDoS 
		attack has ceased, they indicate this change in status to their 
		respective DOTS servers (the mechanism by which this process 
		takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to the
        CPE or PE Attack Telemetry Detection/Classification Systems
        indicating that the DDoS attack has ceased.
	</t>
	<t>
		The CPE or PE Attack Telemetry Detection/Classification Systems 
		transmit a DOTS mitigation service termination request to the 
		DOTS servers.   This DOTS mitigation service termination 
		request may be automatically initiated by the CPE or PE Attack 
		Telemetry Detection/Classification Systems, or may be manually 
		triggered by personnel of the requesting organization in 
		response to an alert from the CPE or PE Attack Telemetry 
		Detection/Classification Systems (the mechanism by which this 
		process takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers terminate DDoS mitigation service on their 
		respective networks (the mechanism by which this process takes 
		place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to 
		the CPE or PE Attack Telemetry Detection/Classification Systems 
		indicating that DDoS mitigation services have been terminated.
	</t>
	<t>
		The CPE or PE Attack Telemetry Detection/Classification Systems 
		transmit a DOTS mitigation termination status acknowledgement 
		to the DOTS servers.
	</t>
	</list>
    </t>

    </section>

	<section title="Automatic or Operator-Assisted Targeted Service/
        Application Request to Upstream Mitigator">
    <t>
   A service or application which is the target of a DDoS attack and 
   which has the capability to detect and classify DDoS attacks (i.e, 
   Apache mod_security <xref target="APACHE" />, BIND RRL <xref 
   target="RRL" />, etc.) as well as DOTS client functionality may be 
   configured so that upon detecting and classifying a DDoS attack, it 
   signals one or more DOTS servers in order to request upstream DDoS 
   mitigation service initiation.  DDoS mitigation service may be 
   terminated either automatically or manually via a DOTS mitigation 
   service termination request initiated by the service/application 
   when it has been determined that the DDoS attack has ended.
</t>
<t>
   In this use-case, the service/application does not possess inherent 
   DDoS attack mitigation capabilities, and is signaling for upstream 
   mitigation assistance.  This can be an inter- or intra-domain 
   use-case.
	<list style="format (%c)">
	<t>
		A DDoS attack is initiated against online properties of an 
		organization which include DOTS-client-capable services or 
		applications that are the specific target(s) of the attack.
	</t>
	<t>
		The targeted services or applications utilize their DOTS client 
		functionality to send a DOTS mitigation service initiation 
		request to one or more DOTS servers residing on the same 
		network as the services or applications, one or more upstream 
		transit networks, peer networks, or overlay MSSP networks, 
		either directly or via intermediate DOTS relays residing upon 
		the requesting organization's network, the upstream mitigation 
		provider's network, or both. This DOTS mitigation service 
		initiation request may be automatically initiated by the 
		targeted services or applications, or may be manually triggered 
		by personnel of the requesting organization in response to an 
		alert from the targeted services or applications or a system 
		which monitors them (the mechanism by which this process takes 
		place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers which receive the DOTS mitigation service 
		initiation requests determine that they have been provisioned 
		to honor requests from the requesting services or applications, 
		and initiate situationally-appropriate DDoS mitigation service 
		on their respective networks (the mechanism by which this 
		process takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS service status message to the 
		services or applications indicating that upstream DDoS 
		mitigation service has been initiated
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the DOTS servers 
		regularly transmit DOTS mitigation status updates to the 
		requesting services or applications.
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the requesting 
		services or applications may optionally regularly transmit DOTS 
		mitigation efficacy updates to the relevant DOTS servers.
	</t>
	<t>
		When the upstream DDoS mitigators determine that the DDoS 
		attack has ceased, they indicate this change in status to their 
		respective DOTS servers (the mechanism by which this process 
		takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to 
		the requesting services or applications indicating that the 
		DDoS attack has ceased.
	</t>
	<t>
		The targeted services or applications transmit a DOTS 
		mitigation service termination request to the DOTS servers.   
		This DOTS mitigation service termination request may be 
		automatically initiated by the targeted services or 
		applications, or may be manually triggered by personnel of the 
		requesting organization in response to an alert from a system 
		which monitors them (the mechanism by which this process takes 
		place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers terminate DDoS mitigation service on their 
		respective networks (the mechanism by which this process takes 
		place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to 
		the targeted services or applications indicating that DDoS 
		mitigation services have been terminated.
	</t>
	<t>
		The targeted services or applications transmit a DOTS 
		mitigation termination status acknowledgement to the DOTS 
		servers.
	</t>
	</list>
    </t>

	</section>

	<section anchor="Web-Portal" title="Manual Web Portal Request to 
	Upstream Mitigator">
	<t>
	A Web portal which has DOTS client capabilities has been configured 
	in order to allow authorized personnel of organizations which are 
	targeted by DDoS attacks to manually request upstream DDoS 
	mitigation service initiation from a DOTS server.  When an 
	organization has reason to believe that it is under active attack, 
	authorized personnel may utilize the Web portal to manually 
	initiate a DOTS client mitigation request to one or more DOTS 
	servers.  DDoS mitigation service may be terminated manually via a 
	DOTS mitigation service termination request through the Web portal 
	when it has been determined that the DDoS attack has ended.
</t>
<t>
	In this use-case, the organization targeted for attack does not 
	possess any automated or operator-assisted mechanisms for DDoS 
	attack detection, classification, traceback, or mitigation; the 
	existence of an attack has been inferred manually, and the 
	organization is requesting upstream mitigation assistance.  This 
	can theoretically be an inter- or intra-domain use-case, but is 
	more typically an inter-domain scenario.
	<list style="format (%c)">
	<t>
		A DDoS attack is initiated against online properties of an 
		organization have access to a Web portal which incorporates 
		DOTS client functionality and can generate DOTS mitigation 
		service requests upon demand.
	</t>
	<t>
		Authorized personnel utilize the Web portal to send a DOTS 
		mitigation service initiation request to one or more upstream 
		transit networks, peer networks, or overlay MSSP networks, 
		either directly or via intermediate DOTS relays residing upon 
		the requesting organization's network, the upstream mitigation 
		provider's network, or both. This DOTS mitigation service 
		initiation request is manually triggered by personnel of the 
		requesting organization when it is judged that the organization 
		is under DDoS attack (the mechanism by which this process takes 
		place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers which receive the DOTS mitigation service 
		initiation requests determine that they have been provisioned 
		to honor requests from the Web portal, and initiate 
		situationally- appropriate DDoS mitigation service on their 
		respective networks (the mechanism by which this process takes 
		place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS service status message to the 
		Web portal indicating that upstream DDoS mitigation service has 
		been initiated.
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the DOTS servers 
		regularly transmit DOTS mitigation status updates to the Web 
		portal.
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the Web portal may 
		optionally regularly transmit manually-triggered DOTS 
		mitigation efficacy updates to the relevant DOTS servers.
	</t>
	<t>
		When the upstream DDoS mitigators determine that the DDoS 
		attack has ceased, they indicate this change in status to their 
		respective DOTS servers (the mechanism by which this process 
		takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to 
		the Web portal indicating that the DDoS attack has ceased.
	</t>
	<t>
		The Web portal transmits a manually-triggered DOTS mitigation 
		service termination request to the DOTS servers (the mechanism 
		by which this process takes place is beyond the scope of this 
		document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The Web portal transmits a manually-triggered DOTS mitigation 
		service termination request to the DOTS servers (the mechanism 
		by which this process takes place is beyond the scope of this 
		document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to 
		the Web portal indicating that DDoS mitigation services have 
		been terminated.
	</t>
	<t>
		The Web portal transmits a DOTS mitigation termination status 
		acknowledgement to the DOTS servers.
	</t>
	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Manual Mobile Device Application Request to 
	Upstream Mitigator">
	<t>
	An application for mobile devices such as smartphones and tablets 
	which incorporates DOTS client capabilities has been made available 
	to authorized personnel of an organization. When the organization 
	has reason to believe that it is under active DDoS attack, 
	authorized personnel may utilize the mobile device application to 
	manually initiate a DOTS client mitigation request to one or more 
	DOTS servers in order to initiate upstream DDoS mitigation 
	services.  DDoS mitigation service may be terminated manually via a 
	DOTS mitigation service termination request initiated through the 
	mobile device application when it has been determined that the DDoS 
	attack has ended.
</t>
<t>
	This use-case is similar to the one described in <xref 
	target="Web-Portal" />; the difference is that a mobile application 
	provided by the DDoS mitigation service provider is used to request 
	upstream attack mitigation assistance. This can theoretically be an 
	inter- or intra-domain use-case, but is more typically an 
	inter-domain scenario.
	<list style="format (%c)">
	<t>
		A DDoS attack is initiated against online properties of an 
		organization have access to a Web portal which incorporates 
		DOTS client functionality and can generate DOTS mitigation 
		service requests upon demand.
	</t>
	<t>
		Authorized personnel utilize the mobile application to send a 
		DOTS mitigation service initiation request to one or more DOTS 
		servers residing on the same network as the targeted Internet 
		properties, one or more upstream transit networks, peer 
		networks, or overlay MSSP networks, either directly or via 
		intermediate DOTS relays residing upon the requesting 
		organization's network, the upstream mitigation provider's 
		network, or both. This DOTS mitigation service initiation 
		request is manually triggered by personnel of the requesting 
		organization when it is judged that the organization is under 
		DDoS attack (the mechanism by which this process takes place is 
		beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers which receive the DOTS mitigation service 
		initiation requests determine that they have been provisioned 
		to honor requests from the mobile application, and initiate 
		situationally-appropriate DDoS mitigation service on their 
		respective networks (the mechanism by which this process takes 
		place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS service status message to the 
		mobile application indicating that upstream DDoS mitigation 
		service has been initiated.
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the DOTS servers 
		regularly transmit DOTS mitigation status updates to the mobile 
		application.
	</t>
	<t>
		While DDoS mitigation services are active, the mobile 
		application may optionally regularly transmit 
		manually-triggered DOTS mitigation efficacy updates to the 
		relevant DOTS servers.
	</t>
	<t>
		When the upstream DDoS mitigators determine that the DDoS 
		attack has ceased, they indicate this change in status to their 
		respective DOTS servers (the mechanism by which this process 
		takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to 
		the mobile application indicating that the DDoS attack has 
		ceased.
	</t>
	<t>
		The mobile application transmits a manually-triggered DOTS 
		mitigation service termination request to the DOTS servers (the 
		mechanism by which this process takes place is beyond the scope 
		of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers terminate DDoS mitigation service on their 
		respective networks (the mechanism by which this process takes 
		place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS mitigation status update to 
		the mobile application indicating that DDoS mitigation services 
		have been terminated.
	</t>
	<t>
		The mobile application transmits a DOTS mitigation termination 
		status acknowledgement to the DOTS servers.
	</t>
	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Unsuccessful Automatic or Operator-Assisted CPE or 
	PE Mitigators Request Upstream DDoS Mitigation Services">
	<t>
	One or more CPE or PE mitigators with DOTS client capabilities may 
	be configured to signal to one or more DOTS servers in order to 
	request upstream DDoS mitigation service initiation during an 
	attack when DDoS attack volumes and/or attack characteristics 
	exceed the capabilities of such CPE mitigators.  DDoS mitigation 
	service may be terminated either automatically or manually via a 
	DOTS mitigation service termination request initiated by the 
	mitigator when it has been determined that the DDoS attack has 
	ended.
</t>
<t>
	This can theoretically be an inter- or intra-domain use-case, but 
	is more typically an inter-domain scenario.
	<list style="format (%c)">
	<t>
		A DDoS attack is initiated against online properties of an 
		organization which has deployed DOTS-client-capable DDoS 
		mitigators.
	</t>
	<t>
		CPE or PE DDoS mitigators detect, classify, and begin 
		mitigating the DDoS attack.
	</t>
	<t>
		CPE or PE DDoS mitigators determine that their capacity and/or 
		capability to mitigate the DDoS attack is insufficient, and 
		utilize their DOTS client functionality to send a DOTS 
		mitigation service initiation request to one or more DOTS 
		servers residing on one or more upstream transit networks, peer 
		networks, or overlay MSSP networks. This DOTS mitigation 
		service initiation request may be automatically initiated by 
		the CPE or PE DDoS mitigators, or may be manually triggered by 
		personnel of the requesting organization in response to an 
		alert from the mitigators (the mechanism by which this process 
		takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers which receive the DOTS mitigation service 
		initiation requests determine that they have been configured to 
		honor requests from the requesting CPE or PE mitigators, and 
		attempt to initiate situationally-appropriate DDoS mitigation 
		service on their respective networks (the mechanism by which 
		this process takes place is beyond the scope of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DDoS mitigators on the upstream network report back to the 
		DOTS servers that they are unable to initiate DDoS mitigation 
		service for the requesting organization due to mitigation 
		capacity constraints, bandwidth constraints, functionality 
		constraints, hardware casualties, or other impediments (the 
		mechanism by which this process takes place is beyond the scope 
		of this document).
	</t>
	<t>
		The DOTS servers transmit a DOTS service status message to the 
		requesting CPE or PE mitigators indicating that upstream DDoS 
		mitigation service cannot be initiated as requested.
	</t>
	<t>
		The CPE or PE mitigators may optionally regularly re-transmit 
		DOTS mitigation status request messages to the relevant DOTS 
		servers until acknowledgement that mitigation services have 
		been initiated.
	</t>
	<t>
		The CPE or PE mitigators may optionally transmit a DOTS 
		mitigation service initiation request to DOTS servers 
		associated with a configured fallback upstream DDoS mitigation 
		service. Multiple fallback DDoS mitigation services may 
		optionally be configured.
	</t>
	<t>
		The process describe above cyclically continues until the DDoS 
		mitigation service request is fulfilled; the CPE or PE 
		mitigators determine that the DDoS attack volume has decreased 
		to a level and/or complexity which they themselves can 
		successfully mitigate; the DDoS attack has ceased; or manual 
		intervention by personnel of the requesting organization has 
		taken place.
	</t>
	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

</section>

    <section anchor="Ancillary" title="Ancillary Use Cases">

	<section title="Auto-registration of DOTS clients with DOTS 
	servers">
<t>
	An additional benefit of DOTS is that by utilizing agreed-upon 
	authentication mechanisms, DOTS clients can automatically register 
	for DDoS mitigation service with one or more upstream DOTS servers. 
	The details of such registration are beyond the scope of this 
	document.
</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Auto-provisioning of DDoS countermeasures">
<t>
	The largely manual tasks associated with provisioning effective, 
	situationally-appropriate DDoS countermeasures is a significant 
	barrier to providing/obtaining DDoS mitigation services for both 
	mitigation providers and mitigation recipients.  Due to the 'self- 
	descriptive' nature of DOTS registration messages and mitigation 
	requests, the implementation and deployment of DOTS has the 
	potential to automate countermeasure selection and configuration 
	for DDoS mitigators.  The details of such provisioning are beyond 
	the scope of this document.
</t>
<t>
	This can theoretically be an inter- or intra-domain use-case, but 
	is more typically an inter-domain scenario.
</t>

    </section>

	<section title="Informational DDoS attack notification to 
	interested and authorized third parties">
<t>
	In addition to its primary role of providing a standardized, 
	programmatic approach to the automated and/or operator-assisted 
	request of DDoS mitigation services and providing status updates of 
	those mitigations to requesters, DOTS may be utilized to notify 
	security researchers, law enforcement agencies, regulatory bodies, 
	etc. of DDoS attacks against attack targets, assuming that 
	organizations making use of DOTS choose to share such third-party 
	notifications, in keeping with all applicable laws, regulations, 
	privacy and confidentiality considerations, and contractual 
	agreements between DOTS users and said third parties.
</t>
<t>
	This is an inter-domain scenario.
</t>

	</section>

    </section>
    
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>
	DOTS is at risk from three primary attacks: DOTS agent 
	impersonation, traffic injection, and signaling blocking.  The DOTS 
	protocol MUST be designed for minimal data transfer to address the 
	blocking risk.
</t>
<t>
	Impersonation and traffic injection mitigation can be managed 
	through current secure communications best practices.  DOTS is not 
	subject to anything new in this area.  One consideration could be 
	to minimize the security technologies in use at any one time.  The 
	more needed, the greater the risk of failures coming from 
	assumptions on one technology providing protection that it does not 
	in the presence of another technology.
</t>
<t>
	Additional details of DOTS security requirements may be found in 
	<xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements" />.
</t>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
	No IANA considerations exist for this document at this time.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">
<t>
	TBD
</t>
</section>

</middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-requirements.xml"?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6335.xml"?>

   <reference anchor="APACHE" target="https://www.modsecurity.org">
        <front>
        <title>Apache mod_security</title>
        <author>
        <organization></organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
        </front>
    </reference>

   <reference anchor="RRL" target="https://deepthought.isc.org/article/AA-00994/0/Using-the-Response-Rate-Limiting-Feature-in-BIND-9.10.html">
        <front>
        <title>BIND RRL</title>
        <author>
        <organization></organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
        </front>
    </reference>

    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
